this is democracy Now democracynow.org
The War and Peace report I'm Amy Goodman
with nine shik we're going to talk about
John Brennan right now President Obama's
nominee to become the next chief of the
CIA the news agency Reuters is reporting
that Brennan had detailed information on
the agency's torture program while
serving there under President George W
bush official records apparently show
Brennan received regular internal CIA
updates about the progress of torture
techniques including water boarding it's
unclear if Brennan raised any objections
at the time he was made aware Brennan's
confirmation hearing will be February
7th in 2006 he gave an interview with
Frontline on PBS where he said it was
right for the Bush Administration to
quote take off the gloves after the 911
attacks the war or the campaign against
terrorism is going to be a long one um
and that the opposition whether it be
alqaeda or whether it be Iraq doesn't
play by the Marquita quinbury Queensbury
rules and therefore you know the US in
some areas has to take off the gloves
and I think that's entirely appropriate
I think we do have to take off the
gloves in some areas but within bounds
and at the right time and the right way
and for the right reason and with full
understanding of what the consequences
of that might be that was John Brennan
in 2006 when President Obama was first
elected in his first term uh he wanted
to uh John Brennan to be his director of
Central Intelligence there was such an
cry in the human rights community that
John Brennan pulled his name out now
four years later President Obama has
officially uh nominated uh John Brennan
once again to head the CIA Our Guest
John kiraku is about to go to jail was
sentenced to 30 months in prison worked
for the CIA um there while John Brennan
was there uh can you respond to what
John Brennan knew when he knew it and
the fact that President Obama wants him
to be head of the
CIA sure obviously I can't read John
Brennan's mind but I can tell you that
uh at the time that uh the torture
techniques were being implemented John
Brennan was President Bush's director of
the national counterterrorist Center uh
he was also um uh a little earlier than
that the deputy executive director and
then I believe executive director of the
CIA that's the number three ranking uh
position in the CIA so
he would have had to have been
intimately involved uh in um not
necessarily in carrying out the torture
techniques but but in the policy the
torture policy uh either that or or he
had to be brain dead uh because you
can't be in positions like that director
of the national counter terrorist Center
and executive director of the CIA
without knowing what the cia's torture
policies are now I'm surprised frankly
uh also at the fact that there's no
outrage in the human rights Community uh
now that uh Mr Brennan's nomination has
been made U official uh there there was
there was a great hu and cry in 2009
when he was initially uh floated for the
position of CIA director and I'm not
sure why there's a difference between
four years ago and now John Brenan
certainly hasn't changed uh John kiraku
I want to read a comment made by the
judge at your sentencing hearing judge
Leoni binkas sentenced you to 30 months
in prison last Friday saying quote this
case is not a case about a whistleblower
it's a case about a man who betrayed a
very solemn trust and that is a trust to
keep the Integrity of his agency intact
and specifically to protect the identity
of co-workers I think 30 months is
frankly way too light because the
message has to be sent to every covert
agent that when you leave the agency you
can't just start all of a sudden
revealing the names of the people with
whom you worked the judge said John
kiraku can you comment on that statement
sure when judge brinka accepted the plea
deal in October uh she she called 30
months uh fair and appropriate uh I can
only think that with a courtroom packed
full of uh journalists uh on last Friday
uh she decided to seize the moment and
uh and make a statement uh that would be
carried in the in the papers I don't
know what changed between October and
January other than the fact that she and
the prosecution had had several U exp
parte uh Communications what that means
is the prosecutors were able to meet
with the judge related to my case
without the defense my attorneys uh
being present so we have no idea what it
was that the prosecution told the judge
we were not allowed to defend ourselves
indeed indeed uh judge BMA Dei denied uh
75 motions that we made uh asking for
declassification of information so that
I could present a defense in in August
of 2012 after our motions had been
denied my attorneys and I walked out of
the courtroom and my attorney said we
have no defense she won't let us say
anything she won't let us defend you and
so we were forced into plea negotiations
but again I'm not sure why the judge
changed her position between October and
January it was in
explain what that's like in the
courtroom uh when they invoke National
Security that the prosecutor can come
forward and speak privately with the
judge without your defense attorneys
being there yeah I I had never heard of
such a thing before but in August when
we made our 75 motions um we thought
that the judge would block off two days
to hear the 75 in fact there had been a
conversation with the prosecution and so
she uh she blocked off an hour to hear
the 75 motions so we knew we were in
trouble and then at the very start of
the uh hearing uh the prosecutor got up
and said that he uh was requesting a
rule four conversation I didn't know
what this was my attorneys objected and
said if you don't want the defendant to
hear at least allow us to to hear so
that we can uh represent his interests
and the judge said no this is a national
security case I'm allowed an expar
communication with the prosecutors so
the prosecutors went to the bench we
could hear them Whispering they came
back to their table and the judge said
all 75 motions are denied and that was
the end of it we got up and we walked
out of court and my attorney said we
have to negotiate a plea uh J it was
extremely disheartening uh JN Rak uh I
wanted to ask you about the legal
implications of this case and how it
fits into the treatment of government
whistleblowers uh under the Obama
Administration absolutely abolutely to
get to the point you just raised with
John I think the reason judge brinka
changed her opinion between October and
last week is because the government
submitted a secret statement that John
was not allowed to see that played a
large role in the sentencing hearing but
neither the public nor the defendant
were allowed to see the statement which
is very cka esque but in the grander
scheme the W the prosecution of John
kiraku and the war on whistleblowers
using the heavy-handed Espionage Act by
charging people who dare to tell the
truth as being enemies of the state
sends a very chilling message and judge
brinka herself acknowledged that a
strong message had to be sent that
Secrets must be kept but apparently that
only applies to people who are trying to
reveal government abuses and illegality
because all of the people in the White
House and the CIA who revealed
classified
information um and over undercover
identities to the makers of a Hollywood
film Zero Dark 30 have done so with
impunity and with lavish praise wait can
you say can you say specifically what
you're talking about JN reita yes
specifically the White House and the CIA
were very involved in the making of Zero
Dark 30
which pretends to be some kind of
neutral film that implies torture led to
the capture of of Osama bin Laden which
it absolutely did not in that process a
highlevel defense department official
Michael Vickers revealed the identity of
an undercover Special Operations Command
officer um but was not held to account
for that and the CIA revealed numerous
classified pieces of information
including sources and methods so when y
keep going so when the United States
talks about the sanctity of keeping
secrets and both the judge and multiple
statements by United States officials
discussed that they are the biggest
leakers of all and they do so with
impunity I wanted to talk about another
whistleblower targeted by the Obama
administ ation um who has been former
National Security Agency analyst uh he's
Thomas Drake he worked for the NSA for
nearly seven years before blowing the
whistle uh Thomas Drake appeared on
Democracy Now last
March the critical thing that I
discovered was not just the massive
fraud waste and abuse but also the fact
that NSA had chosen to ignore a 23-year
legal regime which been established in
1978 called the foreign intelligence
surveillance act with the foreign
intelligence surveillance court and
which at NSA during the time that I was
not NSA but also in the military flying
on rc135s overseas during the latter
part of the Cold War you was the
contrary the one thing you did not do it
was the Prime director of NSA it was you
know the the First Amendment at NSA
which is you do not spy on Americans and
what did you find without a
warrant I found to much to my to my
horror that they had tossed out that
legal regime that was the excuse of 9/11
which I was told was exit conditions now
prevailed we Canen can do anything we
opened up Pandora's Box we're going to
turn the United States of America into
the equivalent of a forign Nation for
the purpose of a of Dragnet blanket
electronic surveillance that's former
National Security Agency analyst Thomas
Drake JN Rak is one of your clients what
happened to
him yes I represented um both Tom Drake
and John kiraku the government dropped
all 10 felony counts against Tom Drake
and he pled guilty to a minor
misdemeanor the equivalent of a parking
ticket I find it appalling that the two
men who revealed the biggest scandals of
the Bush Administration namely
warrantless wiretapping and torture are
the only two who've been criminally
prosecuted for it and not the people who
secretly surveilled the communications
of Americans and not the people who were
involved in the torture program all of
whom have been conferred immunity by
either the president or by acts of
Congress John
kyaku you're now we are now uh the
president is President Obama did you see
a change between President Obama and his
predecessor President Bush and also when
when you were talking about John Brennan
do you think he should head the CIA what
message do you think that sends and what
has changed in the last four years when
he withdrew his name for consideration
uh in 2010 when my book came out I I was
giving a speech in Los Angeles and a and
a woman asked me a question um about the
difference between President Obama and
President Bush and I'll never forget the
question because it was just so crazy uh
she said um can you explain the cia's
pos position on the Jihad isation of
American foreign policy under President
Obama and I laughed and I said ma'am
with all due respect president Obama's
foreign policy is an extension of
President Bush's foreign policy if
there's any difference at all President
Obama is killing more people overseas
than President Bush ever did uh so no I
I don't think there's any difference at
all between the bush foreign policy and
the Obama foreign policy which I think
really is is a is a shame for us because
there was a wonderful opportunity to
take a different path and to reclaim our
our position as a moral leader uh in the
world so I'm disappointed in that uh
with regard to uh to John Brennan I've
known John Brennan since 1990 uh I
worked directly for John Brennan twice
uh I think that he's a terrible uh
choice to lead the uh the CIA I think
that it's time for the CIA to move
beyond the ugliness of of the post
September 11th regime and we need
someone who is going to respect the
Constitution and to not be bogged down
by a legacy of torture I think that
President Obama's appointment of John
Brennan sends the wrong message to all
Americans you worked with him directly
for him did Brennan receive regular
internal CIA updates about the progress
of torture techniques including water
boarding as Reuters is reporting I I
worked for him when he was a u uh an
analytic uh manager it was before he
really hit the big time under George
tenant but again I think that it's
impossible for him to not have gotten
these briefings for him to to not have
been intimately involved in the policy
by virtue of his his senior positions
some of the senior most positions in the
CIA it's just impossible that he didn't
know what was going on John kiraku uh
you'll shortly be going to prison do you
know exactly when uh your prison
sentence will begin and how are you
preparing for this you're the father of
five children I'm the father of five uh
I don't know exactly when this will be
it'll be sometime in the next uh 4 to 6
weeks
I'll have to report to to a prison
somewhere I I don't know where um it's
frankly very hard to prepare you have to
do things like arrange a power of
attorney uh arrange uh Child Care um I
mean there there are so many things to
do it's it's just overwhelming um my
wife thank God is is very strong and
very tough and very supportive and um
we're treating this like
temporary Duty overseas it was not
unusual for me to go overseas for for
many months at a time sometimes as long
as two years at a time two and a half
years so we're treating this like an
overseas deployment uh I can call my
children uh virtually every day uh if
I'm close enough they can come and visit
me and I'm just hoping for the best how
old are your kids John I have two uh
sons from a first marriage who were 19
and 16 and then my uh
wife and I have uh three children an
eight-year-old boy a six-year-old girl
and a one-year-old boy and what do they
understand well they they know that I've
been involved in a fight with the FBI
for the last year and I told them you
know I've been fighting the FBI and
unfortunately I lost and so because I
lost my punishment is I'm going to have
to uh go away for a couple of years and
I'm going to try to teach bad guys how
to get their
High School diplomas and when I'm all
done with that I'll come home and we'll
live as a family and everything's going
to be okay again John kiraku quickly
before we conclude what advice would you
give to whistleblowers now given what's
happened in your case I made mistakes uh
in my case uh I would say first go
through the chain of command which I
didn't do I should have done uh I would
say if you get no satisfaction through
your chain of command go to the
Congressional oversight committees but
do not remain silent if you see waste
fraud abuse or illegality shout it from
the
rooftops leave it Congress thank you so
much for being with us John kako spent
14 years at the CIA as an analyst and
case officer he's going to jail for two
and a half year thanks so much for
watching this report from democracy Now
Your Daily Independent Global NewsHour
we don't accept advertising or corporate
funding but rather rely on donations
from viewers like you please make your
contribution by visiting democ now.org
we need your support today to keep
bringing you this hard-hitting in-depth
reporting